LLMs paired with the lean proof
assistant have led to breakthroughs in
competition math and more recently the
verification of frontier math results.
Lean is a critical part of this process
because it helps validate the candidate
proofs the LLM spits out. In this
conversation, I asked the creator of
LEAN about how it works [music] and how
it will affect the future of math and
software verification. Could that be the
end of handwritten math? Here's the full
episode.
There's this famous Dysterra quote I
want to start the conversation with.
It's that, you know, program testing can
be used to show the presence of bugs,
but never to show their absence. And in
my understanding is that lean and
formalizing proofs can be used to show
the absence of bugs. And so in your
words, what is lean and how do people
use it to show bugs can't occur in
programs?
L is a programming language. You can
write code, but you can also write
proofs. You can reason about your code.
You can write state properties about
your code and prove them. LIN gives you
machine checkable proofs. You can check
your proofs and get absolute assurance
they are correct. You have uh many
checkers, independent checkers. But you
should view LIN as a platform. You can
write code. You can write properties
about your codes and you can prove them.
>> So could you give a concrete example?
Because when I think of a proof, I think
of what I learned in math. But then how
do you couple that with the software
that we write?
>> Yeah, it's a great question. It's not
that different from math proof. L is
actually very popular for math. But for
for software verification, right? uh
there are two
very different use cases. You can reason
about lin programs. LIN is a programming
language. You can write programs in ling
itself.
Then
a link program is not that different
from a definition you have in math. The
techniques are very similar. But when
you if you want to verify programs
written in a different programming
language that basically two different
approaches.
One of them they translate it's called
shallow embedding. They translate for
rust. This happens today. We have a tool
called that maps rust into ling and you
can verify the ling translation right.
uh and there's another technique called
jeep badging where you have the
semantics you you write a semantics of
the programming language of C in ling
and now you have a you have a data
structure that represents a C program
and you can state properties about it is
almost like your programs become lean
objects right that you can reason about
>> to make it really concrete to give
someone a sense of you know here's this
thing I want to prove about a simple C
program maybe like no buffer overrun or
something like that.
>> What's a step by step where we could use
lean to prove that?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Let's get array. You're
trying to access an array in C. You want
to make sure the index is in bounds.
You're not accessing elements that your
array for example has 10 elements.
You're not trying to access elements 11.
Right?
uh basically can you can write that you
can write in link that uh the value of i
at this point in your program is going
to be greater than or equal to zero and
less than 10 right you you can write
that as a mathematical statement right
uh another way to view is that if you
can express in math what you care about
your program you can verify using l
Right? That's another way to view it.
>> So I have my my C source files and then
somehow there's an equivalent lean proof
that's almost like metadata on top of
the C program.
>> Yes.
>> And that's a line by line proof and lean
will go
>> yes and check.
>> Exactly. People will build automation
for automating the process. uh they're
going to use techniques like triples
that says like uh we have a precondition
some mathematical facts that should be
true before executing that statement the
statement and what is true after right
and then we will have a lot of
automation to to process makes your
proof modeler right I mean uh complexity
is a challenge in software verification
handling the complexity is a big deal
And there were all all these frameworks
for very fine programs. They're trying
to manage the complexity make your
proofs modeler
even with AI now AI can prove things
automatically for us but they have to be
modeler to the proofs if you want them
to scale
>> and what you're saying sounds similar to
in software where you have to write it
cleanly. It needs to be easy to edit and
reason about. So it's almost like a
second software layer on top of the
software. Yes. Yes. You can view this
way. You can also flip and imagine a
future where you're writing the what you
want mathematically precisely and AI
synthesizing the codes and approve that
the code that was synthesized meets your
specification right.
>> Oh interesting. So you could start by
writing what you want to be true and
then
>> ask the AI please. AI is going to just
go and hammer at it till the lean proof
says you're good.
>> Yes. Yes. It feels like science fiction.
Six months ago I would say this is
science fiction but for example now a
colleague of mine Kin Morrison
she a few months ago she started a
project I thought was was six months ago
I would say it's not possible at all.
She said uh we have Z lib this s this
compression library written in C and she
said she creates a very complicated
prompt for AI saying I want you to
translate to ling
ensure the lan version passes the test
suite for for zib then I want you to
prove that if you compress data and you
decompress you get the original data
back it's a really strong property right
a and believe it or not they after one
week succeeded doing the whole thing and
now it's just asking to optimize the
codes
but you cannot break the proofs I mean
you have to keep still proved all the
properties you care about I mean
compressing and decompressing getting
the data back is a really important
property for a compression engine right
yeah This is enrich now. I mean, it's
surreal. I mean,
>> it's I mean, it's crazy. And I hear in
the industry a lot of people, they use a
really comprehensive test suite coupled
with AI to do some really amazing
rewrites cuz they have some more
confidence that the rewrite is accurate
and the AI can check itself. And it
sounds like a specification is even
better than a comprehensive test suite.
>> Yes. Yes. Because with well your quotes
from Dystra captures perfectly, right?
With a test suites you can show the
presence of bugs but not the absence.
It's almost like with the a good test
suite is you you may say well probably
there are no bugs here but is you you
may have a really corner case that's not
covered by your test suite but with a
proof you're covering all possible cases
a and it connects so property based
testing is really popular now people are
writing properties they want to to
ensure they are true but they are
checking with testing, right? But now we
can prove them and you say, "Look,
there's no point testing anymore. I
prove it."
>> It seems like having a a well-written
specification is a superset of a test
suite. But in terms of the human labor
required to create a a reasonable test
suite versus a reasonable specification
um you know how much more work is it to
come up with a great specification
>> varies a lot I mean uh the programs
in many it's not uncommon for someone to
start developing a piece of software and
they don't know exactly what the spec is
right but you know properties property
usually their properties are very clear
in your mind another thing that I tell
people to keep in mind that inefficient
program can give you this specification
usually writing in efficient program is
way easier than writing the super
efficient one that does has many clever
tricks you can write a very this is what
I want in a very naive way and you Ask
the AI look generate efficient version
and optimize and prove that it's
equivalent to my inefficient one.
There are many scenarios. I mean I will
not say this specifications are always
easy to come up with but properties
usually the developers have good ideas
about properties they care about.
uh as inefficient programmer is a spec
rights you can view as a specification
and the technology form of verification
complements testing rights I think your
code from extra captures perfectly
>> and I think I saw this on Twitter
because uh Jane Street was more heavily
investing in formal verification
>> yes
>> and I read their post and they talked
about this I think it was a sell for
some software that was entirely formally
verified.
>> Yes.
>> And the main drawback to why it wasn't,
you know, how much more time would it
take writing a program versus verifying
it?
>> Your example cell 4 is a great example.
This was a major milestone. It's a micro
kernel. They verified done manually was
before AI. This project was done before
AI was a big deal.
And it's a lot. The cost is super
expensive, right? At AWS, we have been
using formal verification for a decade,
but only for the super safety critical
components because it's expensive until
now, right? With AI, it changes the
game.
You have to come up with the spec. But
this is not not the most painful part.
The most painful part is to develop the
proofs manually if you have to before.
for AI and maintain the proofs as you
change the codes. Imagine your
I I've seen people complaining that oh I
I change the program right now I have a
bunch of failures in my test suite and I
have to patch go one by one imagine with
proofs you is the same process you have
to fix the proofs uh sometimes you don't
remember anymore why
the pro what what's the story behind
this proof is a lot but we AI is
extremely good at proving
uh writing formal proofs, maintaining
formal proofs. For example, yesterday I
was
changing something. I want to modify
some proofs for technical reasons and I
I didn't even know what the proofs were
about. Someone else wrote then I said,
"Look, I want you to I asked the write
these proofs without using this feature
because I'm going to change it. I don't
want to break the libraries
instantaneous. It came up with the new
proofs for me. I mean it's really good
[snorts] and this is crucial for making
formal verification mainstream because
otherwise maintaining the proofs. It was
almost like if your program took x
amount of time to do the formal
verification in the past would take 10x.
That would be normal.
But imagine if your program is changing.
That's something that's really common.
Now you have to keep maintaining the
proofs too. It's a lot of work. But AI
eliminates uh this pain for us.
>> You mentioned that lean is because I I
hear it as a proof assistant. But
>> and then you also said it's a
programming language. Yeah.
>> Is that typical for proof assistants to
be both a programming language and a
proof assistant? Some of them especially
the ones that are based on dependence
type theory
uh they are like rock and le are
programming languages and proof
assistance right I mean uh uh you can
write definitions
uh like uh when we're defining concepts
in math but some of these definitions
can be programs I mean and you have
types you have structures
is a programming language but is in that
the family of called functional
programming language I mean is a
specific kind of programming language
for people that are familiar with
programming languages like Haskell ling
is close to Haskell I mean but with the
support for proofs that that's a way to
to view ling
>> are there major use cases where people
use it as programming language but not
as a proof assistant
>> well the first big use case is link
implemented in l we have many of our
tooling is implemented in l like the the
documentation authoring system called
vers is implemented in ling. The build
system that's called lake. It's like
ling make lake is implemented in ling.
Uh at AWS we have a compiler for AI
acceler accelerators.
It's half million lines of ling and it's
using ling as a programming language.
They're proving some properties about
the program using ling. But the main
goal is choose ling use ling as a
programming language in this project.
The proofs are like a a bonus right that
you can get the proofs and find problems
in the design.
>> I think most people are familiar with
programming languages and the tool
chains they have and but um what are all
the major components that you would need
for a proof assistant?
>> This is not that different. I mean if
you're used to modern programming
language like Rust the tooling for
example lake is is our cargo right I
mean uh you're going to open v visual
studio codes same way and you're going
to get all the intellisense
one big difference is that we have
something called the info view in ling
your screens usually is going to be
split in two you have your your file on
the right hand side you have the info
view that tells you information about
your proofs, about your codes, uh is
giving you constant feedback about your
developments. That's basically the main
difference, but the tooling, VS code,
everything works the same way. I mean,
>> it seems like a programming language is
the the fundamental layer and then
there's some additional layer on top
that keeps
>> track. Good question. uh uh in L you
have definitions that are your program
but you have theorems statements like
you're going to say for example uh
factorial is always greater than or
equal to zero or something like that or
if you add two even numbers you get even
number you can write statements like
that and immediately you can write
actually a program that's the proof
but most people don't do that they go
into something called tactic modes. You
can view as a domain specific language
for writing proofs in ling. When you
write by it switches to this domain
specific language and you can you have
steps like simplify my goal
the state of my proof. You can say oh
apply this writing step apply for
example we know that x plus 0= x. You
can ask ling apply this writing and
you're going to see in the info view the
state of the proof changing you you get
immediate feedback and you get this
feeling that you said you you keep
telling applying transformations to your
proof step by step you can see what's
happening until you get no goals left
and you are done the proof's complete
and some people view this process as a
game I I have users that told You built
my favorite computer again for me.
[laughter]
>> That's funny. Is lean itself verified in
lean?
>> Lean is a massive program. You only have
to trust the kernel. The kernel is where
the proofs are checked. Lean itself is
the kind of program that because there
are so many new things we are adding.
It's not even clear what is the
specification. For example, what is the
specification of a simplifier? You you
can write general ideas but users they
want to be able to customize the
behavior. They keep asking they keep
changing the specification all the time.
I want this, I want that. No add this
knob here. So it's really hard to have a
full specification of L. But the kernel
is possible to have a specification. We
have a kernel. The kernel that comes
with ling is not verified. But there are
other kernels that you can use. One of
them is implemented by Mario Kanedo.
It's called Ling for Ling and it's
implemented in ling and he's very fine
is proving that this this kernel has
been verified with respect to the
semantics of ling. This is a cool
project but for us having multiple
kernels is the best way to ensure that
your results are correct. I mean uh some
users implemented their own kernels. We
have kernels implemented in rust uh in
different programming languages. Uh
>> and when you say kernel what's what's
the responsibility or what's the inputs
and outputs of that portion?
>> Yes. And l proof checking is type
checking. This kernels they are type
checking your programs. I mean basically
you can export your lan developments.
You got a big blob and you read this
blob and they're going to check if
when you say we have a proofing link
basically you have a thumb that has a
type and you're checking if the type of
this T matches the type that you claim
it has. For example, the example of the
even numbers. This is a typing link
saying that's uh uh the sum of two even
numbers is a even number.
You can write you can view that it is
exactly a typing link and the proof what
the kernel is checking is whether the
type of the proof matches the type you
claim this thumb has I mean and the the
console will check you do this type
checking
uh the kernels vary between
high performance kernel should it's like
5,000 lines of code I mean the goal of
the should be something you can write
yourself.
Uh of course sometimes people put bells
and whistles like uh one thing concern
people have is like okay
but how do I know that I wrote fas
in ling how do you know that when you
exported it's really theorem it's not 2
plus 2 equals four I mean uh and people
some external kernels they write print
printers I mean they will print the
statements that has been proven all the
dependencies
you can have all the these fancy tools
to make sure you're not being misled.
>> Lean obviously it's so powerful and I
see on social media all these amazing
results from formal verification want to
know you what are the top ones that you
think of or top examples more recently
that have impressed you that lean was
able to accomplish? Well, there are so
many I mean that I thought were was
impossible for for example getting a
gold medal in the international
mathematical olympiad.
A few years ago everybody thought was
impossible. Now everybody they use it as
a benchmark of a easy problem. They say
oh this is like a IMO problem. I mean
this is easy but it's not. I mean these
are really challenging problems. Uh the
other conjectures that people close
using ling AI with ling also impresses
me. Uh there's this unit distance
conjecture for others. First open AI
prove it using formal right was not
formal and we have a system now in ling
is a website where we call ling where we
collect challenges.
uh the same Kim Morrison saw this this
this this
proof open AI and she puts on Lo as a
challenge say okay I want to see someone
formalizing we knew it was huge to
formalize
it's serious math it depends on
and Boris Alexi from openi he did his
swim it's a one million line proof for
for for whole proofing link for this
conjecture uh We estimate I mean the the
the ground math that is needed for the
proof we knew it take months I mean for
experts to do by hands. I mean
>> uh how long did it take in that case
like the time from when the proof came
out to when the challenge was solved on
the lean?
>> I think what was one month?
>> Yeah. And after Kim was a few I think
less than two weeks after Kim puts as a
challenge only vow I took I think two
weeks to get the the or or less I mean
>> that's that's insane.
>> Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
>> We talked about verifying programs but
also there's using it just directly for
mathematics like in this case.
How popular is lean in in terms of um
when you look at the users of lean? What
percent are using it for software
engineering? What percent are using it
more for just direct math? Well,
historically lean be got popular first
with math, right? I mean know with the
beginning of the le mathematical library
in 2017
we we had like a big project called
liquid stencil experiments.
Uh it started beginning of 2020. It was
a big deal because it was to verify a
result from a fields medalist. Per shows
it is a result he was unsure about. He
has not published it. uh uh he felt like
this was one of the most important
results in his career. He wanted to be
sure it was correct. It was done
manually. The verification
uh was a big deal because the team that
formalizes led by Yuan Kling
they not only formalized the results
without fully understanding they do not
fully understand the the proof.
uh but having this info view helped them
guides them step by step
they formalized and simplify the proof
without fully understanding the proof is
mindboggling right I mean how can you
simplify a proof from one of the
greatest living mathematicians without
fully understanding it I mean but you
you they manage to simplify it's almost
like when people do factoring coding you
start changing the codes
is faster now But the program doesn't
really know why. I mean, it felt like
that. It's like you have a gut feeling.
I mean, that's you're going the right
direction.
And this for us at the time, lots of
people got excited about link the math
community because of this project. it
like it's shown that's not about
verifying but enabling people to work
together in large numbers because you
can trust you don't need to trust
someone else's proof right they can fill
holes for you
uh this was
I mean what attracts a lots of attention
from the math community then came Terren
St. He starts using after this project.
He has really cool projects with and
without AI and he got addicted actually.
I think the first time he used it said I
don't think I'm going to do it again.
The for proof one week later he had
another project using ling and he did a
new result he had. [laughter]
>> When you say addicted you mean because
that game that like completion engine.
>> Yeah. Some people I I feel we feel like
when I talk to professors that use link
for teaching
they tell me the class is more or less
split. Some people love it, some people
don't like. But people that like to
problem solving, people that get medals
in the IMO, they love because you get
this excitement of solving. It's like a
solving millions of really hard pseudoc
problems, right? [laughter] And you can
keep solving one and it's easy to get. I
mean I'm a lean developer not a lean
user but when you're developing ling I'm
coding in ling and sometimes I have
prove things is really easy to get
addicted it gets lost proving things you
get this bus every time you prove
something [laughter]
>> you mentioned the II gold medals how is
lean used in that kind of uh I think
maybe referring to alpha proof by deep
mind or maybe something else
>> yes deep mind because they got in 2024
was a big surprise in 2024 they got a
silver medal and now we have gold medals
from startups like a harmonic by dance
got a medal I never imagined by dance
they they they're behind tick tock right
I didn't even know they care about form
math but they have a for math team they
got medals also the approver is really
good
>> so how's it work let's say I mean
there's a series of math problems lean
is just used for verification right so I
imagine there's other components there
>> yeah there's the AI you can view it's
like uh we have go that was very popular
with AI the AI is playing the game I
told you that many people see lens again
it's the same I mean the AI is viewing
lens again they have the statements of
what you want to prove you have the buy
keyword words. Now you have a blank
fill. Make sure that you have no goals
left, right? It keeps applying steps in
this game and seeing the trans the state
of the boards, right? That's the info
view changing
and the AI they use reinforcement
learning for for for trying to get to to
no goals left. They it's a single player
game. Some people play together these
days but yeah the AI is learning to play
the game.
>> So before we were talking about that
game it kind of starts with the
specification. So in that case then the
problem is kind of the specification and
then it
>> the problem yeah you have basically for
each problem in the international
mathematical olympiad someone translates
to ling the statements. It's super
important to have the mathematical
library because you want to be able to
talk about the problems, right? For
example, the problems uses the real
numbers. You need a definition in ling
and we have it inside of math lib the
ling mathematical library. So the first
thing you have to be you have to be able
to write the problems in lane and this
now because of math li it's easy part uh
and after that you have to provide the
proofs I mean sometimes some problems
you have to come up with a definition to
some objects you have to to create that
has some property but yeah that's how it
is. I remember you said one of the first
use cases of lean was um this fields
medalist had this novel mathematics and
then we use lean to verify it but can
lean be used with LMS to generate novel
mathematics or just verify existing is a
good question I mean we don't see lots
of evidence we see now evidence it can
find novel proofs
Right? But coming up with new
mathematical concepts is still
at the limits. Right? I mean right now
in this line of all we have challenges
where the AI has to come up with the
objects
uh themselves right I mean but this is
people will keep investing in this area.
I I do not batch against AI here. I
mean, but we we right now we don't have
evidence they can come up with new math.
>> Open AAI, Enthropic, Cursor, and
Verscell all use this product to make
their lives better. And the problem it
solves is when you're building SAS or an
AI product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's SKIM, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So let's say you have a new SAS
product and you want to sell to other
companies. Work OS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you. You
can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. when I see
on Twitter this, you know, major
conjecture, they made headway on it,
it's that they made headway on
confirming something
>> or or disproving. They also have uh uh
this 1 million lines, they shown the
conjecture was false. They have a proof
showing that it's false, [snorts] but
but it's a formal proof. They did not
came up with a new
theory or anything like that. They're
coming up with a proof, right? I mean,
>> at what points would you say someone
should evaluate formalizing something in
lean?
>> I I I think if if it's safe if it's
critical or if you don't understand
really well, I mean this is important
part. I don't really understand. Anybody
that went through the process of
formalizing something understands the
subject way better after that. I I
almost feel like I remember when I was
in college people would say wow after I
implement this algorithm now I
understand it much better.
The next level is that you implement the
algorithm you prove the properties you
expect
your level of understanding grows.
Right? I mean, uh, another cool thing is
that it enables you to to be much more
bold on on your optimizations
because sometimes
I I've seen that all the time people
fear implementing optimization because
they don't really understand why the the
piece of software works. They feel like
if I do that still works and is faster,
but they are not confident with proofs.
you eliminate this discomfort, right?
You you can prove it's again or the AI
can prove for you or find a counter
example. They're good at both things.
But if you were to speculate or draw
into the future, maybe 3 to 5 years from
now, if the cost of formalizing things
goes down, how does that change
software? How does that change um you
know, handwritten math? Oh, I think
we've changed dramatically, right? Uh,
we have to keep in mind the big labs,
they only start training for formal
verification lean very recently, right?
Seriously, before that was like, oh, is
in the data sets. I mean, you don't
really have the the enforcement learning
pipelines to to optimize.
The behavior we see today that is
already amazing will get way better in
the future.
uh the costs will reduce programming
languages like ling and rock will become
more mainstream because of that
uh many people are not so in the past
people say oh functional programming h I
don't like it
but if I'm not the one that's writing
most of the codes anyway
it doesn't really matter what matters
are the specification level right
doesn't really matter how the code has
been written. Yeah, I think it will
change a lot because of that. At least
that's the direction we are pushing
into.
>> What about let's say you know 10 years
from now lean is everything's going
really well with lean. Is that the could
that be the end of handwritten math or
handwritten proofs?
>> I think there will be always aspects
that is handwritten. The
some people like to make a proof look
they they want to use the proof as an
artifact. You communicate ideas to
others. I can't imagine there will
always be people polishing making them
super easy to understand for for another
human to communicate ideas to other
people. There will always be people like
that. The same way today we have people
that uh we have machines that build
furniture but people they like to to
create them by hands and polish them
make them perfect. This will always
exist but it will be a mixture. I I
would be surprised as if there's someone
that's completely
AI is not in their workflow somehow
right I mean you'll be hybrids many
hybrids some people don't like feel this
uncomfortable about this future but for
me super exciting because I view
developing software is super painful
process
and with AI it's crazy how it bring you
awareness of how many steps are just uh
repetitive
and there's no creativity you're just
patching things and AI automates removes
lots of this pain right I mean
I cannot go back to
I'm looking forward to this future you
describe
>> yeah I guess the thing that gives people
I mean I'm guessing The discomfort is
the worry that if it kept going then you
know then we need less mathematicians or
less computer scientists or something
like that.
People don't see that AI can bring more
people. Uh uh there's also the
specification. I mean some I've see
people saying oh we are going to leave
AI we'll come up with new math. But if
there's no connection to our world,
this is some alien thing that's going by
itself. You need an interface. Uh for
example, we want to build programs
because you want to accomplish
something. Uh just something whatever it
is has an specification. There will be
always humans in the loop saying this is
what we need. This is what we want.
Right? writing this interface
interacting with the AI.
The AI will have math libraries and
everything to prove things about these
these programs we are writing these
artifacts this this whatever we are
trying to build
but we have to be able to interact these
libraries we have to understand the
abstractions that are there
I I don't see humans being eliminated we
are always going to be there in the
interface
righth uh we are telling them what we
want right I mean uh specifications will
be there I can see people always writing
codes
uh even another thing a lot of people
like to write they say I love coding my
interpretation is they love to write
prototypes
I this is fun this is the fun part to
try a new idea but to transform it into
a product is never fun I can tell you
it's never fun
and I can take over these parts and
nobody really likes doing
>> outside of lean. I I know you worked on
the Z3 SMT solver
>> and that sounds like a really difficult
thing to build. So first, what is that
solver in your words? And um yeah, how
does it differ from a SAT solver?
>> Yeah, I s long is going to be yes 20
years ago. I started history. I mean
when I joined Microsoft research
uh yeah this is a semmit to solver is
like a set solver but you have
backgrounds theories like you [snorts]
have support for arithmetic
for arrays uh these are not random
choices right this is because we use for
doing test case generation in software
for doing software verification
link fully Z3 is fully automated is a
push button although lens Z3 are called
ton provers. They are completely
different beasts. Z3 is fully automatic.
Ling is interactive. Has automation but
it's interactive.
Tree is not a programming language. It's
like you can do is more like a
constraint solver.
It turns out you can prove simple things
about it. Not you cannot do advanced
math with abstract math. you can solve
constraints with with Z3.
>> What's an example of the the inputs to
this SMT solver and what you get out
from it?
>> Oh, I I can give you one. I mean that's
even in the Z3 manual. Uh you can encode
a sudoko problem as a set of constraints
and you can ask Z3 to solve and will
give you back the answer
instantaneously.
For real applications, Z3 was used very
successfully for finding bugs in
software. Uh people would convert for
example suppose that you have a path in
your code you know that's has a security
vulnerability but you don't know which
inputs to the program allow you to
execute this path. you can convert that
into a set of constraints that you send
to Z3 and it will say unsatisfiable
which means is impossible to execute
this path and you are happy or it gives
you back an example saying look with
this inputs you're going to be able to
do it I mean and people use it for doing
software verification
uh but because the problem becomes
undecidable
at that level you have many universal
quantifiers for stating properties about
your program, your pre and post
conditions.
The server has heristics
and this was all before AI. The
heristics were handcoded and they will
always fail and for simple things people
would be very happy with the push the
fact that Z3 is push button. But when
the property is not trivial, they would
come back saying come on I know the
proof. I mean why is it we can't find it
that's why ling started I started ling
to make sure that we would have a system
that's really good for software
verification right for Z3 was successful
for finding bugs but not so much for
software for proving the absence of bugs
it was never super successful there but
len uh was born to fill this gap
>> you that undecidable but in practice in
the real world if you run it does it
typically terminate?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Great question. Uh uh Z3
goes the whole complexity level, right?
You you have sets uh uh you have NP
complete, P space complete, XP complete.
You have the whole undecidable, right? I
mean uh surprisingly even for sets you
can write really tiny set problems that
are really hard to solve. No set solver
will solve them. But in practice, the
problems we get for hardware
verification,
uh, uh, especially if you bound
everything, you say, "Oh, I'm trying to
look for a bug in the first 10 steps,
right? Everything's bounded. You're not
trying to prove, but you're trying to
capture a class like a space of
scenarios, right?
They are very effective than there. I
mean there I I I think the lesson there
is that programs and hardware
they're not correct by esoteric reasons
right they they are correct for very
simple reasons I mean that's why these
tools are super effective they [snorts]
um yeah but when you get to undecidable
and you're trying to prove even if the
property is not trivial there I mean it
runs out of team I mean and they time
out frequently and [snorts] sometimes
the there's a here a colleague of mine
here at Amazon I mean like chooses the
name proof instability
because sometimes if you change the
problem you just flip I mean you have A
and B you write B and A where B and A
are complicated formulas you may fail to
prove and when she was just trying to
maintain things proof would break if
using this kind of technology. But with
lean, she she switches to lean and super
smooth, right? Because you're
controlling uh the proof
>> in the lean case. Why is it so much more
efficient?
>> Your proof is basically you can view the
sequence of steps for solving the
problem.
In in Z3, you can view that you have
only one proof step. solve, right? I
mean, you're saying you have options to
solve flags, but you have very you don't
you cannot influence what Z3 is going to
do. It's much harder to influence this
kind of system.
In in ling you can if you want to give a
step super detailed stepbystep proof you
can you can use proof automation like is
available in Z3 but you can also break
it down step by step and the fact you
can do that humans can do it but the
happy surprise is that AI can do it
because now you can say step by step why
something is true. the AI can convince
lean that
it can provide a proof. I mean
>> when you were working on Z3 and lean,
what was the most technically
challenging
part that you had to build for for
either project?
>> I understand how much harder ling is in
comparison of Z3 this is or of a
magnitude harder. I mean uh one explan I
I talked to many colleagues about that
why I felt like L was so much harder I I
think it's the surface the interface
with humans is way
for the tree you have defined as a
language for it's called SMT lib it's
very simple language it's not meant for
humans it's meant for tools I mean it is
uses just the back ends of many
different tools
Someone's gener some program is
generating input for Z3 and people
expect a counter example or saying it's
impossible is unsatisfiable to come up
with the counter example. The interface
is really really simple, right? You you
can view it as a command line tool that
you pass this file on this very low
level language that's super easy to
parse and you come back with yes or no.
And l you have is a programming
language. You have libraries. You have
mechanisms. You have interactivity. You
have user interface. You have LSP. You
have build system. You have G. You have
that is so vast. I mean that's
another challenging part for me as I
mentioned Z3 was a back end.
The Z3 users
are very sophisticated software
developers people that speak the same
language I speak. It's way easy easier
to talk to people that speak your the
same language with L is completely
different, right? The B the first users
are all math math people. They have
completely different backgrounds,
different expectations, different
everything and a different community
and then you have people that want to
use L as a programming language. You
have I I I'm not a programming language
person. uh my background is automated
reasoning
and yeah it's different language
different expectations
>> was there like a a singular component
that was just really technically
challenging
>> I I told you that l implemented in ling
of course it was not always like that
right I mean it had to be implemented in
something else at the beginning the
switch from origin origally was C++.
The switch from CC C++ to lean was
extremely painful. Really really uh I
remember I literally want to cry when
when I managed to compile Ling. I was
just uh Sebastian and I at the time were
building L for together
and but this was before we had a
nonprofit for Ling. I remember calling
him and I said, "Wow, man. This is
insane."
Say, "Are you not excited?" He said, he
said, "Yes, I am. I am." I mean, super
excited. [laughter]
>> What What made that switch uh hard?
>> The first thing is is imagine you're
going to implement the language in
itself. The first thing you want is to
reduce to minimize number of features as
much as possible. So you want to
implement ling using barebones
features because you're going to have to
be able to compile it with itself.
uh uh then now you have like 100,000
lines more or less uh I don't know the
exact number but was between 100 around
100,000 lines and you start trying
compile you fail the first you cannot
even compile the first file in the
pipeline that that more than 1,000 and
the first one fails then you fix the bug
you can compile the first one then you
can compile the second and you keep
moving and you're always finding
discrepancies between the new and the
old one. I mean and you're trying to
reconcile make things easier for the new
one.
because you want to replace the old one
and this process
is pain and l is a complicated language
because of these dependence types and so
on the proofs
for example
when you're implementing ling you you
still need some proofs there I mean
there are some basic proofs you need but
you have to construct these proofs
without no interactivity nothing bare
bones you have to provide the proof
time. It's almost like programming in
assembly. The proof uh this was also
super painful. I mean, my god.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
But it took Yeah. Many people thought we
we were going to fail. Sebastian and I
would not be able to do it.
>> 100,000 lines is a lot. Like all human
written.
>> Yes. All human written. Yeah.
>> We talked a lot about lean and I know
there's competitors to lean. What are
the pros and cons of the different proof
assistants? You know, in what scenarios
is one preferred over the others? For
instance, the first disclaimer, I'm a
completely biased person here, right?
But I can tell you what users tell me. I
mean about for example one thing the
users love is the fact as l is super
extensible because l implemented in ling
you can add extensions to imagine you're
doing your math proof in the middle of
this math proof and say oh I want this
fancy automation here you can write in
the same file or the AI can write for
you the extension for automating a proof
and it will do it I mean even the AI is
they know about the the fact L is
extensible.
If I ask the AI to isolate an issue in
ling, I give the AI a link file, it will
start writing a ling meta program, a
program about the link tunnels to
validate the conjecture it has about why
it doesn't work. It's crazy. I mean the
I keeps writing link meta extension
there. The fact that L extension is
really popular with so many people for
example there is Patrick Masur he's a
French mathematician
uh he wrote something called Labos
Labose you can he uses for teaching we
have this language for writing the
proofs but he made the language look
like English and he has the info view
now is a point and click you can click
there it gives you suggestions about the
next move that's written in structured
English like you find in a textbook. You
see the the the student has a really
good idea on how to write in formal math
proof and he did that without asking me
any questions and he all this stuff the
point and click the the new language the
new interactivity he did all by himself.
He's not a computer scientist. He he's
has a math degree and he did all this
stuff and it's for English and French. I
mean you can choose I mean you can write
the proofs in French
uh and looks a textbook proof. I mean uh
uh the people that write visualizations
right for you want to visual you're
trying to prove something about a math
object you can write extension that
visualize these objects in your info
view right [snorts] that people that
write new domain specific languages
embedded in link for different purposes
for example for protocol verification
there's a language called veil is a link
you open veil you feel like it's a
different system for protocol
verification, but it's just a link file
with these extensions for protocol
verification. The language for this
writing protocol is a very convenient
way.
These folks wrote the whole thing
without ever talking to us. They only
talked to us after they had done it said
look I want this pass of link to be
faster. That's was the only interaction
we had. uh and so interactivity is a big
deal.
Uh another big deal now is the
mathematical library uh is vast. I mean
for stating problems open conjectures
you need a library to with the concept
to even state the problem right. So le
has a massive library and a massive
community.
Uh the community also plays a big role.
people uh before AI I think now most
people ask questions about link to AI
but in the past people would go to the
lens lip channel
ask a question about ling they would get
an answer in five minutes I mean people
would say human based AI I mean people
would be writing answers instantaneously
to your problems the community played a
big role another one was
we listen to to to our users I mean uh
uh the math I mean if you talk for
example Jeremat was the first user I
mean he has math backgrounds
he he you ask him look he said look I
could ask anything any new feature I
would get back the same day I mean this
the fix the new feature the same day and
this attracts people right I mean
because you are making improvements
making sure the system does what they
once uh uh they come back for more. I
mean uh this also has a huge impact in
growing the community. when I was doing
some research there was this idea I
think you mentioned in this conversation
too there's this uh dependent type yes
>> proof assistance and then there's higher
order logic what what is that difference
there
>> at the beginning uh when I start I won't
choose high order logic because it's
much [snorts] easier to implement I mean
uh the pen types is way harder there
uh
but the math community I mean Jeremy is
the one that convinced me that I would
never be able to attract serious
mathematicians like fields medal level
math people with high order logic.
Right? His his point is like how logic
is good for concrete math but if you
want to talk about abstract objects
uh dependent type theory is way more
powerful and is beautiful is easy to
explain why is called dependent. For
example, you can have a structure in
ling when you have several fields like x
and y are natural numbers or integers.
Let's say they're integers.
You can have another field. The type of
the field is a proof that x greater than
y. The type of this field is x let's
call greater
column. You say x greater than y. The
type depends on the value of the
previous fields. That's why it's called
dependence type theory. You can have
types that depends on the values of
other parameters, other fields and so
on. But the beautiful thing about that
that's in this you have this very small
language that is so expressive
for example this fields now that's a
proof [snorts] you you have to provide a
proof you can view it as invariance I
can only build elements of this type if
I give the x and y like in other
programming languages but I have to give
a proof that the x is greater than y is
impossible ble to construct elements
without providing this evidence, right?
Uh you can do this in variance that's
you don't have to invent invariants,
right? the language just the fact you
have these dependencies you can express
uh in the functions you can have a
function for example that says takes a x
a y and a proof that's y is different
from zero right I mean it's impossible
to call the function if you do not
provide evidence that y is different
from zero this was always cool but in
the past people would say wow providing
this proofs is really annoying but with
AI Now the I can synthesize the proofs
for you. Uh and it's really cool.
>> In higher order logic though could you
express the same?
>> No no that's you cannot you don't have
the you lose the dependencies. For
example one thing that you cannot do in
high order logic. Uh in l
in serious math people you have a bunch
of structures they manipulate. you have
like something a field I mean a ring a
group
you can write a function in ling that
takes a group and he turns a new group a
new structure
you're not man you don't really care
about the elements of the structure you
are viewing the structure as a first
class citizen that's something that the
penet can do easily and in order logic
is you have to play in coding tricks is
a mess. I mean, uh, some people say,
"Oh, it works for math." None of the
mathematicians agree with this
statement. None. I mean, you talk to to
terish,
Jerem,
Kevin Buzzard, Patrick Masu, they would
say, "No, no, you have to do the pens
type theory." I mean,
that's another example for me that
listening to your users is important. If
you want to appeal to this community,
it's totally okay to say I don't care
about this community. But if you care,
listening to what they really want is
importance.
>> So when we think about the the future of
lean, I'm curious to hear your thoughts
on where you think lean is going. Um
things you're excited about in the
future. You know, what might it look
like in in a few years?
>> Yeah. Yeah. One thing uh we have this
nonprofit behind LIN since 2023.
I mean L 13 years old uh the first 10
years was
such project right I mean only when we
got the nonprofits behind ling that it
became you can view as a product we have
a team of engineers
and we managed to do it because the
impact on math right but Sebastian and I
I mean we co-ounded this nonprofit what
we are really excited about is le as
programming language, a programming
language where you can prove things
about your programs, right? And that's a
direction we are pushing really hard,
right? Link to uh uh we are super
grateful for AWS,
Amazon, they they're making the largest
donation so far to these nonprofits
where the goal is to accelerate this
path. I mean, LIN is doing super well in
the math path, but let's make Ling as a
programming language. lings a system for
social verification, harder
verification. Let's push to the extreme.
Let's give some love to these people uh
uh to this path that's right now we do
not really have funing to push seriously
this path. That's the nonprofits, right?
Uh for me to be in a world where you can
reason about your codes uh uh is part of
my life. They I'm not writing testes
anymore. I'm writing properties and
proving them. The AI is proving most of
them for me. Uh this is direction we are
pushing hard. And one people one thing
that people don't realize is that when
you have proofs it enables optimizations
for free. You can ask the for example
today if you ask the AI to optimize you
have to inspect the code to make sure no
bugs were introduced in the process.
But
if the AI is telling you, look, I
optimize it. It still computes the same
thing. Here's the proof.
Uh this is a game changer in my points
of view.
>> Yeah, I've heard multiple people say
this decade will be the you the decade
of formal verification of software and
yeah, maybe, you know, lean will be a
huge part of that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We we for sure we're super
excited to make it happen. I mean uh we
uh
scalability is super important, right?
Because there's a big difference between
math and and social verification. In
math the the statements are usually
really tiny or small. I mean the is an
example. I mean super small but the
proofs insanely cheap.
for socialification
is the opposite right these statements
are big I mean but the proofs are
shallow the reason why this is true is
shallow but you have to manipulate this
big objects right
>> so for someone who wants to um learn
more about formal verification or learn
more about lean do you have a top
technical book recommendation
>> in the lean websites I mean we have uh
several books there that's introduce
lean functional programming lean theorem
proving lean mathematics in lean the
mechanics of proof is great for for
educational purposes we have we have a
collection of books if
people go to lind-lang.org or they they
you'll find all these books there.
But one one thing I I tell people these
days is that learning
l using AI is super efficient. I mean
you you keep talking to AI in natural
language asking what do you want asking
it to write examples many people split
the screen in three now right we had the
link codes the info view and on the
bottom now many people now using an AI
agent there that's writing the codes and
explaining natural language what's going
on there it's a super effective way I
mean Aren style he told me when he
learned ling he he uses old version of
it was before agents he [snorts] would
have the shajp on one window and the
visual studio code in the other window
and he would copy and paste between them
and that's how he learned but now he's
even more effective with the AI agents
it's easy to pick up I mean just talk to
the agent sometimes people say how do I
that start talking to the agent. He will
help you. here will customize
uh right you can explain what you know
already right I mean what's your
backgrounds and for example if you tell
oh I know hasll it's so much easier
right you can customize the process
>> and then last question for you is you
know if you could go back to the
beginning of you know building C3
building lean and give yourself some
advice knowing what you know now what
would you
>> [laughter]
>> No, I'll keep it a secret. I mean, I
think ignorance is a bliss. I mean, you
don't know how hard things are and when
you start the adventure, maybe I'll keep
secrets. What I would tell I think one
thing, especially before starting I I'm
super introverted
and I would tell look you should work on
your people's skills. I mean, because it
helps a lot. I mean when you have to
interact with a community with people
for me it was hard to to learn that and
and I would tell myself look it's really
important to have people's skills too.
>> Well thank you for your time today
appreciate it.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey thank you for watching this podcast.
If you liked it and you want to see the
show grow, please support with a comment
or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker. These were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within
eight hours of launching. I really
appreciate it if you were one of the
people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um, we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and I'll see you in the next